<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The crovvne of righteousnes: or, The glorious reward of fidelity in the discharge of our duty. As it was laid forth in a sermon, preached in S. Botolphs Aldersgate, London, Sept. 25. 1653. At the solemn funerall of Mr. Abrah: Wheelock, B. D. the first publick professor, and reader of Arabick, and of the Saxon, in the University of Cambridge. Whereunto is added, an encomium of him. / By William Sclater Doctor in Divinity, now preacher of the Word of God in Broad-street, Lond.</title>
            <author>Sclater, William, 1609-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S916</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E221_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4044</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872581</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872581</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125020</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94261)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125020)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 38:E221[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The crovvne of righteousnes: or, The glorious reward of fidelity in the discharge of our duty. As it was laid forth in a sermon, preached in S. Botolphs Aldersgate, London, Sept. 25. 1653. At the solemn funerall of Mr. Abrah: Wheelock, B. D. the first publick professor, and reader of Arabick, and of the Saxon, in the University of Cambridge. Whereunto is added, an encomium of him. / By William Sclater Doctor in Divinity, now preacher of the Word of God in Broad-street, Lond.</title>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1609-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. G. for John Clarke, and are to be sold at his shop under S. Peter's Church in Cornhill.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654. [i.e. 1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Thomason copy bound with other items from October, 1653.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 31".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wheelocke, Abraham, 1593-1653.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 2nd, IV, 7-8 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125020:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CROWNE OF RIGHTEOUSNES: OR, The glorious Reward of FIDELITY In the Diſcharge of our DUTY. As it was laid forth in a Sermon, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in S. <hi>Botolphs Alderſgate, London,</hi> Sept. 25. 1653. At the ſolemn Funerall of Mr. <hi>Abrah: Wheelock,</hi> B. D. The firſt Publick Profeſſor, and Reader of <hi>Arabick,</hi> and of the <hi>Saxon,</hi> in the Univerſity of <hi>CAMBRIDGE.</hi> Whereunto is added, An <hi>ENCOMIUM</hi> of HIM.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM SCLATER Doctor in Divinity, Now Preacher of the Word of God in <hi>Broad-ſtreet,</hi> Lond.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DAN. 12.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>They that be wiſe [or, Teachers] ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the Firmament, and they that turn many to righteouſneſs, as the Starres, for ever and ever.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. G.</hi> for <hi>John Clarke,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop under S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:125020:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:125020:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipfull <hi>Thomas Adams,</hi>
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Alderman of the City of <hi>London,</hi> a Patron of Learning, and a Patterne of True Piety, the eternity of Happineſs.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which I have in my inward thoughts ſecretly wiſhed for, the Divine Providence hath now (by an unexpected Act) preſented to my hands; a ſeaſonable opportunity, wherein I might make you ſome more than a private Teſtimony of my acknowledgements, for your perſonall regards to my ſelfe; and withall, as publick as might be, for your munificence to my ever honoured Mother, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>Cambridge;</hi> where, for above twenty years laſt paſt (out of a pure glory to God, in the advancing the Orien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Learning) you erected, and ever ſince continued, at your own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per coſt, an Arabick Lecture; the praiſe whereof were a task more meet (I confeſſe) for an elegant Orator choſen by her ſelfe, than for one of my ſo retired, and obnubilated a condition.</p>
            <p>The much lamented deceaſe of the learned Profeſſor, Mr. <hi>Abrah: Wheelock,</hi> who read it, (and of whom a more full mention is made in the cloſe) gave occaſion to this ſudden Sermon; which being through a vehement importunity, extorted from me, beyond all imagination of mine own, after preaching, and ſo put to the Preſs; there could be no more proper Patron for it thought upon, than your ſelf, of whom I have many things to ſay, but that I am overwhelmed with copiouſneſs of matter; there being no ſpirituall, or good gift wherein you are, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of his Converts, the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.7</note> behind, yea wherein you do not excell: your very outward preſence, as ſome rare beneficent ſtar, appearing with a deſired and pleaſing influence, winneth you a venerable obſervance of all Orthodox Chriſtians, and good men; who cannot depart from you but much improved, and made better by your moſt eximious, and tranſcendent example in<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 1.6. Act. 24.16</note> all piety towards God, &amp; equity towards men: I need not mention your Ethicks or moral part, ſith if the vigorous exerciſe of all the vertues were not interrupted only, but loſt elſewhere, it might be all repaired from your<note n="†" place="margin">Eph. 5.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> accurate practiſe: in your religious part an Iſraelite<note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 1.47</note> indeed, without faction, without ostentation: your ſoule is made the<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.16.</note> Temple for the Holy
<pb facs="tcp:125020:3"/>Spirit to dwell in by his graces, which are diffuſed in ſo delectable a variety; that, as thoſe fragrant ſpices, upon which the South winde blew in the Garden of the ſpouſe, they<note n="d" place="margin">Cant. 4.16.</note> flow out, and are become as a ſweet perfume to attract Obſervers.</p>
            <p>To men of learning a known <hi>Maecenas,</hi> yea, a Sanctuary; To Gods faithfull Miniſters an<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 12.13.</note> hospitable<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 16.23.</note> 
               <hi>Gaius,</hi> a bountifull, and a moſt encouraging Benefactor,<note n="g" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.12, 13. 1 Tim. 5.17.</note> eſteeming them highly in love for their works ſake: of all Gods<note n="k" place="margin">Pſ. 122.1.</note> publike Ordinances a due honouror, a moſt conſcientious<note n="l" place="margin">Act. 26.7</note> frequenter: In private alſo the devotion of your houſe hath made it an houſe of<note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor. 16.19.</note> devotion, where, like the double mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the lungs, what is drawn in by prayers, is breathed forth again in<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 118.15.</note> prayſes and thanksgiving: Your faith is operative<note n="o" place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> working by love, expreſſed<note n="p" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.18.</note> in rich<note n="r" place="margin">2 Cor. 9.13. Prov. 11.25.</note> liberality towards every good work, full of<note n="s" place="margin">2 Cor. 9.7.</note> cheerfull<note n="t" place="margin">Act. 10.2.</note> Almes-giving, the<note n="u" place="margin">Job. 311.20.</note> loynes of the poore and naked bleſſe you in the ſtreets, and the bowels of many<note n="w" place="margin">2 Tim. 1.16.18.</note> refreſhed by your hands, as S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s were by <hi>Oneſiphorus,</hi> occaſion unceſſant prayers for you: And that which yet adds a beauty to all the reſt, and proves alwayes as the most rich, and faireſt<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a curious Knot.</note> knot, decking the garment of other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is your great<note n="x" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.5</note> humility, attended with all<note n="y" place="margin">1 Pet. 3.8</note> courteous affability, and moſt<note n="z" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.6 Col. 3.13. 2 Pet. 1.7.</note> kind<note n="a" place="margin">Ro. 12.16.</note> condeſcenſions; as in whoſe lips is the<note n="b" place="margin">Pro. 31 26</note> law of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and in whoſe life a<note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 1.15</note> ſhining exemplar of the<note n="d" place="margin">2 Ti. 3.5.</note> power of godlineſs, and all ſolid Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>All which conſidered, my weak endeavours cannot but triumph in ſuch a protection, which now they ſhrowd themſelves under, not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſpeed the better for the Name of the Patron: The diſcourſe, I acknowledge, is impolite, yet Orthodox, I hope, and Thelogically ſubſtantiall, the ſubject matter is no leſs, than of a <hi>Crown of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs;</hi> ſo that however, as it comes from me, it caſteth no great luſtre outwardly, yet much what like to the ſtone <hi>Garamantides, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus habet aureas guttas,</hi> it hath drops of gold within it ſelfe, enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the believing ſoule with the hopes, and aſſured expectation of a joyfull reward of its fidelity in Gods ſervice by a bliſsful immortality.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the certain fruition whereof, that you, and with your ſelfe all yours, all your relations, yea, all Gods<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 24.</note> elect by Chriſt, nay, after you have yet continued longer to<note n="f" place="margin">Tit. 2.10:</note> adorn the Goſpel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be at last advanced, is, and ever ſhall be the moſt conſtant prayer of, Sir,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt affectionate Servant to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Lord Chriſt,</hi> Will: Sclater.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:125020:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 TIM. 4.7, 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the Faith: Henceforth there is laid up for me a Crowne of Righteouſneſſe, which the Lord, the Righteous Judge, ſhall give me at that Day: and not to me only, but unto them alſo who love his Appearing.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall not deteine you by any impertinent Preface, ſith the ſhortneſſe of time for this Service, together with the indulgence of this ſo Learned an Auditory, anticipates an Apology, and gives hopes of much Candor, under ſo manifold Impraepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>And ſo I addreſſe my ſelfe to the ſerious buſineſſe of my Text; The ſcope whereof amounts to this ſumme, Namely, to comfort <hi>Timothy</hi> about the nigh approach of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Martyrdome, mentioned, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. The argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Conſolation are two, each depending on the other. 1. The firſt taken from his Holy courſe of life, conſtantly conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, comfortably finiſhed, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. 2. The ſecond, from the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:125020:4"/>certainty of his Bleſſed eſtate, aſſured to him after this Life, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. And indeed, the Apoſtle ſeems to put on him the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a dying<note n="*" place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.11.</note> Father, willing to inhibit, or at leaſt to<note n="a" place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.13.</note> moderate the paſſions (which like Ambergreeſe may doe well in a compound of grace) of his indeared children, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſing, as<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 49.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>Jacabs</hi> Sons, his Death-bed; as if he had thus<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 32.2.</note> dropt his words upon them: <hi>What doe ye thus</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 21.13.</note> 
               <hi>weeping, and breaking my Heart?</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.10.</note> God, my owne<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 9.1.</note> Conſcience, your ſelves are witneſſes, how holily, and without crime, I have<note n="g" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.17.</note> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the time of my ſojourning here, God, by his grace hath (according to his promiſe)<note n="h" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.18.</note> preſerved me<note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.8. 1 Theſ. 3.13.</note> blameleſſe unto the end: You know what happy things he hath<note n="k" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9.</note> prepared for them that love him, into the<note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 11.40.</note> Beginnings whereof my Soule ſhall enter, at my<note n="m" place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> Diſſolution; the<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> fulneſſe, and conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation I expect at that great and<note n="o" place="margin">Act. 2 20</note> notable day of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Reſurrection, and Retribution: Right ſo the Apoſtle here, to the ſame effect, to comfort <hi>Timothy,</hi> whom (having<note n="p" place="margin">2 Tim. 1, 2. and 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten him ſpiritually through the Goſpell, to the Faith of Chriſt) he found even as a Naturall<note n="q" place="margin">Phil. 2.22.</note> Son, with his Father moſt affectionately tender, obedient and obſervant, unto his very laſt expiration: I am now ready to be offered, and the time of my departure is at hand; (yet nevertheleſſe be comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for) <hi>I have fought a good fight,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and henceforth, there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. This for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, and ſcope of this Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have fought a good fight.</hi>] The expreſſion is borrowed from thoſe who ſtrive for<note n="r" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.25. 2 Tim. 2, 5.</note> maſteryes, and after a ſharpe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, or heate of Contention, doe at laſt prove<note n="s" place="margin">Rom. 8.37.</note> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have finiſhed my Courſe,</hi>] id eſt. <hi>Curſum certaminis, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eſt corum, qui in stadio currunt,</hi> as <hi>Eſtius</hi> expounds it; The ſpeech being taken from ſuch as runne in a race, who give not out till the prize be obtained, ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24, 25, 26. <hi>I have kept the Faith.]</hi> That is, That Fidelity, or truſt, and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which he had conſtantly made good in the diſcharge of his Apoſtleſhip, and Miniſtery, in preaching the Goſpell far and neere, throughout many<note n="t" place="margin">2 Cor. 10.14.16. Gal. 1.16.</note> Regions, from the time of the firſt Commiſſion of the ſame, unto his<note n="u" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.17.</note> Diſpenſation: The
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:125020:4"/>Apoſtle in his owne practiſe, accompliſhing that, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in all other the Stewards of like ſacred Myſteries, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. for this alſo, he gave God thankes, for counting him faithfull, in putting him into the Miniſtery, committing the glorious Goſpell unto his<note n="w" place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.4.</note> truſt, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.11.12. upon which he was aſſured of his, <hi>Euge, Bone ſerve, &amp; fidelis. Well done, good and</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 25.21.</note> 
               <hi>faithfull Servant, enter into thy Maſters joy.</hi> Ere I come to the more particular elucidation of the parts, I may not omit to mention thoſe quaeries, and reſolutions, which ſome of the antient Fathers have not unprofitably raiſed, and given upon theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaer: </seg>1</label> The firſt whereof is this; <hi>Whether Saint</hi> Paul <hi>did not, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this profeſſion, boaſt in a kinde of vaunting oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this Saint<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> Chryſ. in Loc.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> makes anſwer thus;<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, He doth not magnifie himſelfe, or boaſt in any way of vaine-glorious<note n="z" place="margin">Non haec jactantiae verba ſunt, ſed bonae Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, <hi>Eſtius ad Loc. 1 Cor. 10.31.</hi>
               </note> Oſtentation, (a ſin which, elſe where, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely cautions againſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16.) but they are the words of a Saint, uttered in a modeſt, meek, and humble proteſtation, whereby he owneth the graces of God within him, and gives all the
* glory in their vigorous exerciſe, to God the Originall Fountaine, and beſtower of them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaer: </seg>2</label> Quaeſt. <hi>Whether Saint</hi> Paul <hi>did well to Commemorate, and make mention of his gracious Actions, and good Deeds?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> makes anſwer thus; <hi>Fas eſt viris ſanctis in morte recordari, imo &amp; recolere virtutes vitae actae,</hi> &amp;c. It is lawfull for Holy men, and Saints of God, in Death to recollect, and to recount the vertuous deeds of their former lives paſt; Not indeed, as an occaſion of exaltation in themſelves for the ſame; But, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t fiduciam praebeant, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperantem timorem premant,</hi> for the ſuppreſſion of feare, and Deſperation, in the laſt Houre; in as much as good workes are the<note n="a" place="margin">Jam. 2.18.</note> fruit of a ſaving Faith; that, as Faith juſtifies the perſon in a Correlation to Chriſts merits, (it as an hand<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 5.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> receiving, apprehending, and applying them as all-ſufficient to the ſoule) ſo good workes (being the way to eternall life, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10.) Declaratively, and Praeſentially juſtifie the Faith, ſhewing it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:125020:5"/>not to be Counterfeit or dead, but Reall, and living; It being the innate property of ſuch a Faith to be<note n="c" place="margin">Vera ſides viva eſt, Nec poteſt eſſe otioſa. <hi>Juell. in Apolog</hi>
               </note> vivacious, manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelfe in its godly<note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> Operations: Hence was the ſaying of the Schoole Divines, that <hi>Charitas</hi> was <hi>forma virtutum,</hi> Charity (which is the<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 13.8.</note> ſumme of the Law) conſiſting in love towards God, for his own ſake, and towards our<note n="f" place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.14.</note> Neighbour, for Gods ſake, it was the Forme of the Theologicall Vertues; Not but that Faith, and Hope, and other graces of the Spirit, have their owne ſeverall and particular Formes, which doe ſpecifically forme them to their owne Identicall Natures, and diverſifie them from others, ſo that Faith is not Hope, nor Hope is not Charity; but for that love, doth as it were, forme them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptability before God, to this purpoſe may be applicable that practiſe of zealous <hi>Nehemiah, Chap.</hi> 13.14. <hi>Remember me, O my God,</hi> (ſaith he) concerning this, <hi>and wipe not out my good Deeds, that I have done for the Houſe of my God, and for the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices thereof:</hi> and the like is that we alſo read of good King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> upon a Summons to Death, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.3. And he ſaid, <hi>Remember now, O Lord, I beſeech thee, how I have walked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, in Truth, and with a perfect Heart, and have done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaer. </seg>3</label> A third Quaerie is, <hi>Whether Saint</hi> Paul <hi>ſpake all this, as out of a ſelfe-confidence, without having an eye to Gods Divine aſſiſtance therein?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which, ſaith venerable <hi>Bede, Abſit ut tantus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ignoraverit legem Dei, Deut.</hi> 8.17. God forbid that ſo great a Doctor ſhould be unacquainted with the word of God, which teacheth utterly to diſclaime all ſelfe-power, though it were but to become wealthy, or potent, even in things Temporall; yea, himſelfe ſeriouſly acknowledgeth all ſpirituall ſufficiency to be of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. evermore aſcribing the totall of his ſupernaturalls to the free grace of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. through whoſe ſtrength alone it was that he diſcharged his Truſt in the Goſpell, and went through with all other graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous performances, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaer: </seg>4</label> The fourth, and laſt Querie is, <hi>How Saint</hi> Paul <hi>came to know ſo aſſuredly, that there was a Crowne of Righteouſneſſe laid up for him in Heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:125020:5"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which ſome anſwer, That he had it by Revelation extraordinary, as an Apoſtolicall priviledge daigned to him from God, the better to chear him on in the courſe of the Goſpell, and to ſteele his reſolutions againſt all oppoſers of the glorious Truth therein revealed: or, as <hi>Anſelme</hi> thus, He had that aſſurance, <hi>Non re pleniſſimâ, ſed spe firmiſſimâ:</hi> grounded upon a firme hope, and expectation: But of this more anon.</p>
            <p>Having thus pointed at the Quaeries: I come now to the more particular handling of the words, out of which I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve two generall parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A ſolemne Profeſſion of the diſcharge of his Office, <hi>verſe</hi> 7.</item>
               <item>2. A large Remuneration, and Reward of that Diſcharge, <hi>verſe</hi> 8.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In the former, we have 1. The Perſon, <hi>I.</hi> 2. His Act, <hi>fought.</hi> 3. The object of that Act, <hi>A fight.</hi> 4. The quality of that fight, <hi>A [good] fight.</hi> 5. The time of all this, noted from the expreſſion in the <hi>Praeter tenſe, I [have] fought</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I have fought a good fight:</hi> the reſt of the words in this verſe I take to be, upon the matter, but as the exegeſis, and expoſition of the former.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond maine part, The reward; We have it ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. 1. By the Donor, or beſtower of it, The Lord, deſcribed here by a Periphraſis, and ſtyled, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judge.</hi> 2. By the Title given to it, <hi>A Crowne of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</hi> 3. By the manner of it, <hi>it is laid up.</hi> 4. By the time of Donation, <hi>In that Day.</hi> 5. By the perſons to whom beſtowed, <hi>To Paul himſelfe;</hi> and that, not by any reſtrictive encloſure, as if onely to himſelfe, and to none other beſides; but by a farther expanſion, it reacheth unto others with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; provided they be found under due qualification of loving the appearance of the Judge; Not unto me onely, but unto them alſo that love his appearing.</p>
            <p>Theſe, at leaſt, as to my obſervation, are the parts of this Scripture; which being ſo many, I muſt be conſtrained, as the Diſciples paſsing through the Corne-fields upon the Sabbath day, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to pluck but an eare,<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 2.23.</note> or two of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:125020:6"/>choyceſt notice; or as ſome Lapidaries of rich Jewells are wont, ſhew them onely in a ſhort curſory view, and ſo lay them up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            <p>The firſt words, <hi>I have fought a good fight,</hi> admit of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Interpretations, yet each of them ſuitable to the Analogy, and<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 12.6.</note> proportion of Faith.</p>
            <p>They may then be taken, either as the expreſſion of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe, <hi>quatenus Apoſtolus,</hi> as under the notion of an Apoſtle: or elſe as a Chriſtian, in the condition with other Members of the Church of Chriſt with himſelfe, for that we read in the cloſe of the eighth verſe, <hi>The Crowne of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was laid up for all that loved the appearing of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we take them in the former ſenſe, then from the firſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, <hi>The Perſon;</hi> The note of<note n="h" place="margin">Magali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus, ad loc.</note> 
               <hi>Magalian</hi> is appoſite, <hi>Stus Paulus Dux fuit, &amp; anteſignanus eorum quae praecipiebat;</hi> That we looke at Saint <hi>Paul</hi> as an Exemplary leader to all his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, (though indeed not in an Apoſtolicall Latitude, yet) in the office, and worke it ſelfe of the Miniſtery, practically firſt doing what he would have others to obſerve in, and about the diſpenſation of the Goſpell: ſee <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.9. And this was our Saviours owne Courſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.1. He began to doe and Teach, firſt to doe, and then to Teach; its noted by <hi>Barradius</hi> upon that Propheſie, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. which had relation to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, it was ſaid, <hi>The Government ſhould be upon his ſhoulders,</hi> intimating, that himſelfe would firſt beare in his owne perſon, what he intended to impoſe upon others, to wit, in things capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Imitation; even as he ſaid unto <hi>John Baptist,</hi> when he cender'd himſelfe to be Baptized of him, and he in an humble renuence grew ſhy, as deeming himſelfe unworthy of ſo great an Honour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Suffer it to be ſo now,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for thus it becommeth us to fulfill all Righteouſneſſe; Haec eſt enim Iuſtitia, ut quod alteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facere velis, prior ipſe incipias, &amp; tuo alios horteris exemplo,</hi> as Saint<note n="i" place="margin">S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> in <hi>Luc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> expounds the words; This was righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, that is, an equal, and juſt thing, that what thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt have another to obſerve, and do, thou thy ſelfe ſhouldeſt firſt exemplifie in thine owne actions ſuitably; whereunto was that ſerious adviſe of S. <hi>Paul</hi> unto his Son <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:125020:6"/>
               <hi>Take heed unto thy ſelfe, and unto thy Doctrine, for ſo thou ſhalt both ſave thy ſelfe, and thoſe that heare thee;</hi> Where the chiefeſt heed was to be given to himſelf: Truly ſpake<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Saint</hi> Gregory in Job <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> Saint <hi>Gregory, cum Imperio docetur, quod prius agitur, quàm dicatur,</hi> Then ſhall we with Authority ſpeake what we doe, when we doe what we ſpeake: But this is a Diſcourſe fitter for a Viſitation, than a Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall; were it not, that it is at the obſequies of ſuch a worthy Divine, (for whom we now performe this laſt Chriſtian good office) whoſe practiſe herein was an accurate Comment upon the whole ſpeech.</p>
            <p>From the ſecond and third particular, (in this acception of the words) its obvious to every apprehenſion, that the worke of the Miniſtery is a Fighting, yea, a continuall Warfare: ſo <hi>Bruno,</hi> and with him<note n="l" place="margin">Espenceus ad Loc.</note> 
               <hi>Eſpencaeus</hi> obſerves, that where the Verbe and Subſtantive run in the ſame termes, one conducing to, the other to perfect the Emphaſis of the expreſsion, there is ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more a [Frequency] of that Act implyed: I ſhould but caſt drops into the Ocean, to endeavour a large proof of ſo clear a Truth: Whileſt <hi>Noah,</hi> both by his Lips and by his Hands (in<note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 11 7.</note> buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Arke) was a<note n="n" place="margin">2 Pet. 2 5.</note> Preacher of Righteouſneſſe, in the old world, was it not thus? whilſt the ſpirit of God (in his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery)<note n="o" place="margin">Gen. 6.3.</note> ſtrove with the obſtinate corruptions of that wicked world, what aſperſions, what oppoſitions, what miſuſages, and abaſures had the Prophets in their dayes, being<note n="p" place="margin">Ier. 20.7.</note> derided, traduced,<note n="q" place="margin">2 Chro. 36.16. Mat. 23.37.</note> miſuſed, inſulted on, even for the Conſcientious diſcharge of their Function? The pretious Sons of <hi>Sion</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to fine Gold, how were they eſteemed as earthen Pitchers, the worke of the hands of the Potter? <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.2. And, who knowes not the exact accompliſhment of old <hi>Simeons</hi> Prophecy of our Saviour himſelfe, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.34. How he was ſet for a ſigne, which was and ſhould be<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>In ſignum contrad ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le.</hi> Tert. de Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne Chriſti, cap. 28. Iſ. 8.13.</note> ſpoken againſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for a ſigne of contradiction, he ſhould be as a common<note n="s" place="margin">Illirio. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Hall <hi>in Paraphr:</hi> Piſcator &amp; Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas.</note> marke, whereat the arrowes of reproach ſhall be fully ſhot: Of all the Holy Apoſtles its noted, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. They were made as the filth of the world, and the<note n="t" place="margin">Confer. Lam. 3.45.</note> off-ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all things continually; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifieth that reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, which is ſcraped from the dirty pavement, from whence the ſhooes gather defilement; and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it being a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:125020:7"/>word in a Compoſition, carryes with it the greater Emphaſis, and denotes the polluted rakeings of the ſtreets, fit for nothing but the common Dunghill; In ſo low a ſtate of abjection, and in ſo vile an eſteem were thoſe very<note n="u" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> Ambaſſadors of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, among an Atheiſticall and<note n="w" place="margin">Act. 2.40. Phil. 2.15.</note> crooked generation: our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Apoſtle here profeſſeth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32. <hi>That he fought with Beaſts at Epheſus,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſome would have meant Literally, of his being dilaniated, and rent in his body, (as many Primitive Chriſtians were in the firſt Cruell times of raging perſecution) by wilde Beaſts to which <hi>Nero,</hi> that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicator Damnationis,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt.</hi> in Apologet.</note> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſtyles him, being himſelfe a<note n="y" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.17.</note> Lyon, was wont Tyrannically to caſt the bodies of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: But others better, in my poore underſtanding, expound it of thoſe Ethicall or Morall Beaſts, who with <hi>Demetrius,</hi> and the rabble that cryed up the great <hi>Diana</hi> of the Idolatrous <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians,</hi> ſo violently withſtood and oppoſed Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who cryed downe that their abhominable ſuperſtition at <hi>Epheſus, Act.</hi> 19. in which place a great door, and effectuall was opened unto him, but there were many<note n="z" place="margin">1 Cor. 16.9.</note> Adverſaries, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.8, 9. thoſe Apoſtles indeed experimenting the proofe of what their Lord and Maſter foretold them, that they muſt be ſent forth even as Sheep among<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 10.16.</note> Wolves, who would attempt to teare them in pieces: and which of us in particular, encounters not his diſcouragements? Yea, woe is me! We ſeeme to be fallen into thoſe times, wherein many men (as if directly<note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 6.10</note> infatuated from Heaven) out of a groſſe miſpriſion apprehend the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery it ſelfe the greateſt inconvenience; and (that great cheat, that grand Pantomime of Chriſtendome, the cunning Jeſuit (now almoſt bare-fac'd) hath inſtilled (as is feared) ſo pernicious a principle into ſuch as are (for ought we can ſee) willing to be deceived, as to queſtion the<note n="c" place="margin">1 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1. Rom. 11.13.</note> office it ſelfe, and to diſpute the Inſtitution; as if they would have men ſcorne the Phyſitian when ſickeſt, and ſhun the Chirurgion when ſoreſt; And (which muſt not be forgotten) there are not wanting ſome, who are apt to charge on that ſacred Calling, the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, if not the cauſe of all the Calamities of this latter Age: juſt as thoſe of whom <hi>Suidas</hi> reports, that they were wont to write with Inke or blood on a glaſſe, and ſo ſet it againſt the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:125020:7"/>Moon, making all thoſe ſpots or blurres that were in the glaſs, to be in the Moon, and not at all in the glaſſe, upon which alone they were written: meane while, never at all anatomizing their owne Ulcerous, Corrupt inſides, or repenting for their<note n="d" place="margin">Prov. 13.5. Ezek. 36.31.</note> loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſelfe-abhominations (and among them as principall, for the contempt of <hi>Gods faithfull Miniſters.</hi>) Which ſins becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſo Epidemicall, and Nationall, as they are, call for Wrath and Indignation from that Lord, who is here ſtyled in my Text, <hi>the Righteous Judge.</hi> And yet, though this be <hi>a Fight,</hi> nevertheleſſe it is, for the quality, <hi>a [good] Fight,</hi> and that for theſe reaſons;</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, becauſe its undertaken for the<note n="e" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.12.</note> Faith of Chriſt, and for the Salvation of Soules, whereof even one ſingle one is more worth than a<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 16.26.</note> whole World; O what comfort will it be, in the day of retribution, when a<note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.2.</note> faithfull Miniſter, after all his ſharpe conflicts with the<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 2.40.</note> wayward oppoſitions of corrupt men, ſhall ſay; Loe me, and the<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 8.18. Heb. 2 13.</note> people, which thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, as the fruit of all my labour in thy Goſpell, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thus to give up an<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> account with joy, and not with griefe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe its undertaken for a good reward, which is no leſſe, than a <hi>Crowne of Righteouſneſſe;</hi> What S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaid of afflictions for a good Conſcience, will hold here alone, <hi>Conſideratio praemii minuit vim flagelli,</hi> The conſideration of the Reward, abates of the Difficulty of the Fight; even ſo its noted of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that having reſpect unto the recompenſe of the reward, he preferred the reproach of Chriſt to all the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt treaſures in <hi>Aegypt, Heb.</hi> 11.26. the ſame was it likewiſe that animated that noble Prophet under all his diſcouragements, and fruitleſſe endeavours among men, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.4. <hi>I have labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in vaine, and spent my time for nought, yet ſurely my Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is with the Lord,</hi> and my worke, that is, the reward of my worke is with the Lord; who rewardeth his Miniſters, <hi>ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dùm laborem,</hi> though not <hi>ſecundùm proventum,</hi> as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes, according to their Labour, and pious endeavours, which themſelves undergoe in the Goſpell, though not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſucceſſe of their Labours, which is<note n="k" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.6.</note> Gods alone to beſtow.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:125020:8"/>
            <p>And thus farre of the words, in their firſt acception, uttered by S. <hi>Paul</hi> as an Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>I might next conſider them alſo, as ſpoken in the name of all other Chriſtians at large, even of all ſuch as, who love the appearing of the Lord Chriſt Jeſus at his comming.</p>
            <p>And under that notion of them, we may obſerve, That the Life of a Chriſtian is a continuall warfare upon the Earth, ſo <hi>Chryſologus, Chriſtiano militare eſt, id quod vivit in ſeculo,</hi> ſuitably unto that of <hi>Job, Chap.</hi> 7.1. Where the word rendered <hi>an appointed time,</hi> is by many tranſlated a <hi>Warfare,</hi> which was hinted to us in the firſt<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 3.15</note> enmity between the two ſeeds; after againe, in <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 25.22.</note> ſtrugling together in the ſame wombe; and to this effect is that ſpeech of our Saviour, <hi>I came not to ſend Peace on the Earth, but War, Diviſion</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 10.34, 35.</note> 
               <hi>and variance,</hi> namely, between Grace and Corruption; which was experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented mightily in the breaſt of this our Apoſtle, when the <hi>Law in his Members rebelled againſt the Law of his Minde, Rom.</hi> 7.23. it was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a warring Law; and elſewhere he ſaith, <hi>The fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, as the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit luſteth againſt the fleſh, Gal.</hi> 5.17. and to the ſame purpoſe alſo Saint <hi>Iames, Chap.</hi> 4.1. <hi>From whence come Warres, and Fightings among you? Come they not hence, even of your Luſts, that Warre in your Members?</hi> Surely Contention comes from Corruption; ſee likewiſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11.</p>
            <p>Now, I might here take occaſion to treat of the Doctrine of the ſpirituall Warfare, and purſuing the Metaphor, preſent you with thoſe ſeverall things that concurre to make up a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate Battaile; as 1. A Bickering, and encounter it ſelfe, <hi>Niſi praeceſſerit pugna non poteſt eſſe Victoria,</hi> as Saint<note n="o" place="margin">S. Cypr. li de Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. c. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian,</hi> there cannot properly be ſaid to be a Victory, where never was a fighting, <hi>delicata jactatio eſt, ubi periculum non eſt,</hi> its but a fond, or eſſeminate kinde of boaſting of a Conqueſt, where never was danger. 2. In a Warre there muſt be Enemies, with whom to encounter, <hi>quis enim certat niſi inimicum habet?</hi> ſaith <hi>Prosper,</hi> there cannot be a Contention, where there is not an Adverſary: Now in this Warfare, the great and the grand Adverſary is the Devill, who, with an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is ſtyled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The Adverſary, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.7. He
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:125020:8"/>is as the chiefe Champion, the World alſo and the Fleſh as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sunt tria quae tentant Hominem, Mundus, Care Daemon.</hi> And in relation to the ſeverall Temptations of each of theſe, Schoolmen have given them diſtinct names, or Titles, being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by them, either <hi>Obrepentes,</hi> or <hi>Aſcendentes,</hi> or <hi>Immiſſa:</hi> Thoſe which are from the World ſeeme full of ſlattery, and creep on, after a ſort, inſenſibly, and deceive us; Thoſe from the fleſh aſcend, as it were out of our ſelves, therefore the more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, becauſe the leſſe perceptible, they being ſo pleaſing to Corrupt Nature, and a ſelfe-ſnare: Thoſe from the Devill are ſent from without, with more vehemency, therefore called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Darts <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.16. becauſe caſt into a man; for in very deed the Devilſ<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Macar. Homil.</note> knows no mans Heart, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deales, at firſt, (till after farther experience) by Conjecture; all which (if I had time) it were eaſie to inlarge upon. 3. In a Warre, there muſt be Armes, and Weapons; and to furniſh our ſelves with theſe, we have a full Armory, or panoply in the Holy Scriptures; The whole armour of God we have for all ſorts of Weapons, whether Offenſive or Defenſive, in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.13, 14. &amp;c. 4. There muſt be policies, or ſtratagems in War; meanes to Circumvent, diſappoint, over-reach, overthrow the Enemy, &amp;c. Theſe and many the like, are the parts to make up this ſpirituall warfare: all which muſt of neceſſity, (if, as it ought to be ſpoken to fully) will ingroſſe more time, than I have left to goe through with my other buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, waving that ſo copious a Theame, at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; I proceed on now to the ſecond generall part of my Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, which is the Remuneration, or reward of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> fidelity in the diſcharge of his truſt, in the Diſpenſation of the Goſpell; <hi>Henceforth is laid up for me a Crowne of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Much (but that I ſtudy Brevity) might be ſaid of the Dignity of this reward, it being ſtiled, <hi>a Crowne;</hi> and largely alſo I might diſcourſe of the certainty thereof proved, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly to be made good, partly from the promiſe of God, of that<note n="q" place="margin">2 Theſ. 3 3.</note> faithfull God, who is ever<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 111. 5.</note> mindfull of it, and never diſappointeth a true believer of performance, namely ſo as he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:125020:9"/>promiſeth, <hi>Eſay</hi> 40.10. <hi>Behold, the Lord God will come with a ſtrong hand, and his arme ſhall rule for him, behold his reward is with him.</hi> See alſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.11. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.19. The Pſalmiſt ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, after a ſort, raviſhed, and in a kind of extaſie, tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of himſelfe, in wonder at the meditation, <hi>O how great is thy goodneſſe which thou haſt laid up for them that feare thee, which thou haſt wrought for them that truſt in thee, before the ſonnes of men!</hi> And elſewhere, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.11. <hi>Verily there is a reward for the righteous, doubtleſſe he is a God that judgeth in the earth.</hi> And <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10. <hi>God is not unrighteous to forget, &amp;c.</hi> nor was ever any mans <hi>labour</hi> (maugre the blaſphemie of all thoſe Infidels, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.14.) <hi>in vaine in the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. See alſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. And this is partly alſo to be made good from the meritorious expiation of the Lord Chriſt, the vertue whereof extended not onely to a deliverance from all paine and miſery, which he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by his Paſſion; but alſo to the opening a way to everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing happineſſe, by his all-glorious Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.2. And laſtly, this may be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected likewiſe from the preſent afflictions of Gods ſervants, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5. for elſe, as the preſent caſe now ſtands with them, they are in this life of all men elſe moſt miſerable, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19.</p>
            <p>Now, the Schoolmen have reduced the ſumme of all the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Bleſſedneſſe, and Reward, unto two maine heads, which they ſtile, <hi>Dotes animae, &amp; Corporis;</hi> as it were, the Dowries of the Soule and Body, both which, as they have beene ſharers in obedience, ſo ſhall they alſo be in the Compenſation of the juſt reward. Thoſe of the Soule are theſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The cleare<note n="s" place="margin">1 Jo. 3: 2.</note> Viſion of God, which they ſay is, <hi>tota mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> beholding him<note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12.</note> face to face, namely, ſo farre as a finite Being (for ſo our Humane Nature continues ſtill, though glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied) may be capable to apprehend of that Majeſty, which is Infinite; in this advanced condition, the Soule (which is here clogg'd, and droſſy, and much praegravated by the Body, ſubject to corruption) ſhall beatifically ſee God, as he is, in the full ſplendor of his immortall glory; whereas beneath, it ſeeth onely in part, and knoweth but in part, nor can the greateſt part of our ſublunary knowledge, make up the leaſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:125020:9"/>part of our Ignorance; the diſcovery that we have now of Heaven, is but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as by reflexion from a glaſſe Darkely, being changed into the Image of God, by degrees, from one glory to another, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. but then, all clowds ſhall be diſpelled, the Intellectuall eyes fully cleared up into a perfect and bright ſerenity, and withall enjoy a ſweet oblecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Contentation and Delight accompanying that inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible and bliſſefull Viſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the will, perfect fruition of the Divine glory, tention, and (for the meaſure of the Creature) Comprehenſion, a compleate aſſimilation, and likeneſſe to that glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, in Holineſſe and Righteouſneſſe; In thoſe new Heavens dwelleth nothing but righteouſneſſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the whole Soule, <hi>Joy unſpeakable and full of glory,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. In the Body, 1. Impaſſibility, it is not, nor can be ſubject there to any Ach, Ague, or Paine, no diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or agonizing vexations whatſoever, <hi>All Teares ſhall be wiped away from our eyes, Rev.</hi> 7.17. 2. Agility, expedite quickneſſe, free from all manner of Lumpiſh pondero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, or defatigation whatſoever; Yea moreover, perfect Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and glorious ſplendor, ſuch as the Sun it ſelfe, in its full Brightneſſe partakes not of: Here below the Beauty of the Saints is ſhadowed, and much clouded, partly by the interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Hypocrifie (Copper often paſſing before weake eyes for Gold, Formality for Reality) eclipſing that<note n="u" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.12.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; ſimplicity which would both<note n="w" place="margin">Tit. 2.10.</note> adorne the Goſpell, and grace the purity of profeſſion: partly alſo by afflictions, to which the godly are<note n="x" place="margin">Act. 14.22.</note> appointed in this life, where <hi>Chriſtianus</hi> is <hi>quaſi Crucianus,</hi> and that<note n="y" place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.22.</note> Baptiſme of blood, and Suffering is made the character of a true Believer, as that of Water is of an outward viſible Member of the Church: And partly alſo by Corruption, which like ſpriggs, or ſuckers ſprouting forth even under the choyceſt graffe, will ſometimes be ſhewing of it ſelfe in the defection of our beſt actions, yea, in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of<note n="z" place="margin">Jam. 3.2. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 6.1.</note> Exorbitancy; ſo that whereas, in theſe ſeverall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards, the Beauty of the Saints is much obtenebrized, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoured, yet then ſhall they<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 13.42.</note> ſhine forth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, even as the Sun from out of a Clowd, in full clarity, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulgent
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:125020:10"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> glory; which was praefigured, after a ſort, in that ſhining transfiguration of our Saviour upon the Mount, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. When the viſion was ſo gliſtering, and reſplendent, that <hi>Peter</hi> could have beene contented, (though but from that glimpſe of glory) to have erected a<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4.</note> Tabernacle, for a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſight and Contemplation, he found it ſo ſweet, that it was good to be there longer. 3. Laſtly, To all this may be added Immortality, as the Diamond ſet in the ring of all the reſt, there Mortality hath put on Immortality, the Body never more, after it is cloathed upon therewith, being ſubject unto Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, Death it ſelfe is then ſtruck dead, and ſwallowed up in a finall Victory unto all Eternity: To which purpoſe ye may doe well to meditate at leiſure thoſe very appoſite and perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Scriptures, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54, 55. compared with <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.14. and to this purpoſe the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of bliſſe are ſtyled<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> manſions,<note place="margin">Joh. 14.2.</note> or abiding and reſting places, <hi>John</hi> 14.2.</p>
            <p>And this is the reward, couched under this Metaphor of a Crowne, the Bliſſe whereof, indeed, tranſcends the skill, and tongue even of Angells themſelves to expreſſe: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the excellent goodneſſe was treaſured up, but in the gifts and graces of Regeneration in this life, ſaith even of them, that the naturall eye hath not Seene, nor the eare Heard, nor hath it entred into the Heart of an unſpiritualized man, to conceive the things which God hath praepared for them that love him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. Much leſſe ſurely can this be done, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the<note n="d" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.17.</note> Excellent glory above in Heaven; Wherefore the joy thereof being ſo incomprehenſible, as it is, when it could not enter into the faithfull ſervant mentioned in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, then he was bid to enter into it, even into that joy of his Maſter, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.21. And thus farre of the remuneration it ſelfe at large, both in the Certainty and the Dignity thereof, It is a <hi>Crowne of Righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come next to conſider the Donor, or the Beſtower of the ſame, the Lord, ſet forth unto us here, under the periphraſis of being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Righteous Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where note, ſaith the Roman Catholique, that the Reward is a Reward of Juſtice, not of favour, rendered as a due debt,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:125020:10"/>not given as a gratuitous benevolence, ſo <hi>Cajetan</hi> on the Text, <hi>Dicendo, reddet Juſtus Judex, debitum jus ſignificat;</hi> and, ſo by conſequent, the good workes, to which its rendered, are properly meritorious, and God ſhall be unjuſt if he deny them his due reward, even due of debt: But whilſt theſe overweening ſpiders ſuck poyſon, the Humble Bees draw honey from theſe fragrant and ſweet flowers: To <hi>Cajetan</hi> (though none of the meaneſt Schoolmen) we may oppoſe <hi>Primaſius,</hi> who hath this more ſolid expreſſion, <hi>quomodo iſta corona debita redderetur, niſi prius illa gratuita donaretur?</hi> How can that Crowne be ſaid to be rendered as due, unleſſe firſt it was beſtowed as free? and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>opera Bona ſunt Dei dona,</hi> The Lord in crowning our good deeds, doth but reward us with his owne gifts; in this caſe we muſt be all conſtrained to ſay as <hi>David,</hi> on another oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.14. <hi>All things come of thee, and of thine owne have we given thee;</hi> Wherefore, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (the great Aſſertor of free grace) hath ſtyled moſt fitly life eternall it ſelfe, (wherein conſiſteth the abſolute conſummation of all gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a free gift, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. a word not uſed in any Heathen Author, but peculiarized to the<note n="f" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16. 2 Pet. 1.11</note> inſpired penmen of Holy Writ; beſides, the manner of the Apoſtles expreſſion is very remarkable, even in this very Text, where the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, [is laid up] and the other of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> [ſhall give] both theſe expreſſion simply a free Donation, no meritorious purchaſe at all; elſewhere, our reward in Heaven is called an Inheritance, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18. which is a thing comming freely by deſcent unto the rightfull Heyre: Moreover, workes merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, according to the determination of the Patrons of merit themſelves; They muſt be, 1. <hi>Noſtra,</hi> our owne workes, wrought out of our owne ſtrength, and done by our owne power, whereas the Evangelicall Prophet hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe aſſured us, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.12. <hi>Thou O Lord,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>haſt wrought all our workes in us,</hi> He meanes, gracious workes: Alas, we are not ſuch Silkewormes as to ſpin a thred of Faelicity out of our owne bowells; we muſt remember that the higheſt ſtyle, which the Scripture gives the Saints, is but to be<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 9.15. 2 Tim. 2.20.</note> Veſſells of Salvation, to<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 5.17.</note> receive the graces of God diſtilled into them from above; Not<note n="i" place="margin">Our heart is as barren of any good, as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Iſle of <hi>Patmos</hi> is, where no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will grow, but on earth that is brought from other places. D. <hi>Stough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
               </note> Springs or Fountaines to derive them to our<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tanquam fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae</hi> B ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardin. de S. Paulo.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:125020:11"/>ſelves; and by the very Schoolmen themſelves, the graces of the Spirit are called, <hi>Habitus infuſi,</hi> Habits, not acquiſite by frequent Acts, as morall vertues are, but infuſed by God into the Heart, <hi>Every good and perfect gift deſcending from above,</hi> as Saint <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17. Yea, it was the poſitive aſſertion of our Saviour himſelfe, <hi>John</hi> 15.5. <hi>Without me ye can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> He meanes<note n="k" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.5</note> Acceptably; He doth not ſay, as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> obſerves, <hi>ſine me difficulter poteſtis,</hi> or, <hi>non poteſtis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficere, without me ye can hardly doe any thing,</hi> or, <hi>ye are not able to bring any act unto perfection, but ſimply,</hi> and expreſſely thus, <hi>Without me,</hi> that is, without<note n="l" place="margin">Cant. 8.5</note> leaning upon me, having my ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and gracious aſſiſtance, <hi>Ye can doe nothing at all that is good and gracious;</hi> and our Apoſtle alſo, elſewhere, profeſſeth, that all our ſufficiency, namely in things ſupernaturall, is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſolely of God alone; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. Therefore we may well conclude, that whatſoever good workes there are in us, they be none of our owne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As they muſt be our owne, ſo likewiſe are they, (in the ſenſe of thoſe grand Impoſtors of the Chriſtian world) to be perfect, as in which nothing is to be found defective, nothing redundant; whereas all our righteouſneſſe, as it is inhaerent in us, Alas! it is but as a defiled, naſty, and polluted menſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.6. the higheſt pitch, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of perfection, that (whileſt we are clad with the raggs of our<note n="m" place="margin">Pyil. 3.21.</note> vile fleſh) we, the very beſt of us all, can attaine to in this life, is (as I have ſhewne<note n="n" place="margin">See my Sermon, ſtyled, <hi>The Remedy of Schiſme,</hi> preached at <hi>Pauls Lond</hi> 1640 p. 18, 19.</note> elſewhere) but to ſee, and to acknowledge our imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; as in the cleareſt ſerenity of the Firmament, ſome ſpeckling cloud may be diſcovered, ſo in our moſt accurate and exact performances, either in the Matter, or in the Manner, or in the Degree, meaſure or end of doing, we all prove ſome way defective; even the very beſt things that we doe have enough in them to be pardoned, if the Lord ſhould diſcuſſe them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy in a rigorous ſeverity, and be ſo extreme as to<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 130 3.</note> mark what in them is done amiſſe: To this effect the forementioned School Divines have ſtyled the greateſt Saints, as they are yet Members but of the Church militant on earth, but <hi>Viatores,</hi> wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in the way, whoſe motion is but only progreſſive, not Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſors, till actually inſtated Members of the Church Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:125020:11"/>above in glory, in the meane while, that maxime in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity is Orthodoxe and ſolid, <hi>Succeſſivorum non ſimul eſt eſſe, &amp; perficere,</hi> Thoſe things which admit of a ſucceſſion in their motion, or degrees of growth, their being and perfection is not all at once, nor altogether; wherefore our very Apoſtle elſewhere, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12.15. profeſſeth, though he were perfect, in regard of ſincerity and uprightneſſe, yet not ſo, in regard of the full meaſure; He was ſo in reſpect of Parts, he was not ſo in reſpect of Degrees, therefore he ſaid, that he had not as yet fully apprehended; <hi>Fuit perfectus, ſpe futurae glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis, Fuit Imperfectus, onere Corruptionis; Fuit perfectus, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectatione muneris; Fuit Imperfectus, fatigatione Certaminis,</hi> as moſt appoſitely to our preſent purpoſe,<note n="p" place="margin">Fulgent. lib. <hi>1.</hi> ad Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im.</note> 
               <hi>Fulgentius:</hi> perfect he was, in the Hope of future Glorification: he was imperfect, under the burthen of preſent corruption; He was perfect in the expectation of his reward, but yet imperfect being tyred under the great conflict, and encounter that he had with the oppoſers of the Goſpell of Truth; compleate perfection he profeſſed not; much leſſe may others, ſo farre inferiour unto ſo great, and moſt illuſtrious a Saint, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> was.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Workes meritorious, as they muſt be our owne and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſo alſo (in their ſenſe) <hi>Indebita,</hi> more than due, ſupere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatory tranſcending the Command; whereas (proud Catha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts and brittle pot-ſherds as they are) they might obſerve what the great Law-giver hath declared in that Caſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.10. When we have done all that we are able to doe, we remaine ſtill moſt defective, and moſt unprofitable ſervants, and have at the utmoſt (if we could reach to that) done but duty.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, Works meritorious muſt be <hi>proportionata ad mercedem,</hi> exactly proportionable unto the juſt Reward; but ſurely if (as they cannot) our Paſſions, and<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> Sufferings cannot equall the Reward, much leſſe can our Actions, or our imperfect doings; ſweetly ſingeth the Pſalmiſt, God Crowneth indeed, but it is in his owne mere mercy, and loving kindneſſe, not for any poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible deſert in the primeſt Creature; yea,<note place="margin">Meritu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Domini. <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi>
               </note> it's a maxime in the very Schoolmen themſelves, That <hi>Principium meriti prius eſt merito,</hi> and that <hi>principium</hi> is Gods free Grace, Mercy, favour.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:125020:12"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaer. </seg>
               </label> So then, yeild all this: But, <hi>How then is it free, and yet a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Juſtice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Some anſwer thus, namely, by underſtanding Juſtice, in this Text, of Gods Fidelity, and faithfulneſſe in keeping pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, as in that Text, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.9. where <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are joyned together, if we confeſſe our ſinnes, God is faithfull and Juſt to forgive us our ſinnes: And in this ſenſe, (rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended) its true indeed, to ſay that its <hi>Debita merces,</hi> A re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Debt, becauſe God hath, after a ſort, bound himſelfe by his owne promiſe to give it unto us: <hi>Promittendo ſe fecit Debitorem,</hi> ſaith<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Aug. de verb. Apoſt. Serm. 16.</hi> Debitor Deus factus eſt, Non aliquid â nobis acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendo, ſed quod ci pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittendo— illo ergò modo poſsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus exige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum, ut dicamus, Redde quod promiſiſti, quia feci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quod juſsiſti, &amp; hoc tu fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſti, qui la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borantes juviſti— Non dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Deo, Redde, quia accepiſti; ſed redde, quid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſiſti, <hi>Gonr. Die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teric. Dn. 9 poſt Trin. in Fine.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> he hath made himſelfe a Debtor to his Church by promiſe, in which only regard it is, that we may <hi>exigere Dominum,</hi> as he ſpeakes, urge and preſſe the Lord upon his word, ſo we reade the Church under affliction did, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.21. <hi>Remember, breake not thy Covenant with us;</hi> compare herewith, <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.5. Others more directly give us this anſwer; Aeternall life, is in reſpect of us, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a mere Gratuity, or free gift; But in reſpect of the perſonall merit of Chriſt, its a reward of Juſtice; The Lord Chriſt Jeſus having purchaſed unto all his true Believers, by his Humiliation and Obedience, this Crowne of their Imputative righteouſneſſe, how imperfect ſoever their owne perſonall Righteouſneſſe was: And from this title of the Lord, his being a righteous Judge, all his faithfull Servants may aſſuredly reſt upon the Infallibility of the reward of their Service and Fidelity, ſith the Lords owne word, aequity and faithfulneſſe is ingaged for it; Surely he is faithful who hath promiſed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23. nor can he faile or deny himfelſe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. Yea, he himſelf is our ſhield and our excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great reward; <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. and indeed, in enjoying God, we enjoy all happineſſe, and ſoule-ſatisfying Contentation; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its not impertinently obſerved by the Hebrews, that in the Eſſentiall Name of God <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> all the Letters are <hi>Litera quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentes,</hi> Letters of Reſt, to denote, that without God there can be no ſolid joy, or quietneſſe of Soule, which will ſtill be toſſed in a kinde of reſtleſſe inconſiſtency, till it doe indeed ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate at laſt in him; which made that man, ſo much after Gods owne heart! as in a flame of fervent zeale) experimentally to put the queſtion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25. <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee? and there is none upon earth that I deſire beſides thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:125020:12"/>
            <p>The next particular that fals under my conſideration is the time of donation, when this Reward is to be actually conferred, expreſſed to be [in That Day, and at the Lords appearing.]</p>
            <p>Theſe<note n="s" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.1. and 2 Tim. 3.1.</note> latter times, into which the<note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.11.</note> ends of the world are fallen, abounding (as men in old age) with variety of<note n="u" place="margin">Mund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſeneſcens, patitur phantaſias. <hi>Gerſon.</hi>
               </note> phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, have given us occaſion to enquire, what Day of the Lords appearance it is, which is here meant? whether it be the great. and<note n="w" place="margin">Act 2.20. 2 Tit. 4.1.</note> notable day of the<note n="x" place="margin">Joh. 6.39, 40, 41.</note> laſt generall Judgement; or elſe of ſome other manifeſtation of the Lord Chriſt upon earth, before that laſt day of all doth come?</p>
            <p>There are ſome (otherwiſe abundantly knowing) whoſe wits have herein proved more wanton, than their judgements ſolid, whoſe apprehenſions have led them to conjecture, if not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve an appearance of the Lord Chriſt perſonally, in a way of raigne and triumph, to be manifeſted upon earth, a thouſand yeares before the laſt day of the Generall Judgement: ſuch, in the Greek expreſſion, are called <hi>Chiliaſts,</hi> and by the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines,<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Aug. <hi>lib.</hi> 20. <hi>De</hi> Civ. <hi>Dei</hi> c. 7 <hi>&amp;</hi> Philaſtr. c. 59. <hi>De</hi> Hereſ. <hi>&amp;</hi> Aug. <hi>De</hi> Hereſ. c. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Miſtenaryes:</hi> ſome have fetched the name, and conceit ſo high as from<note n="z" place="margin">Euſeb. 1.3 <hi>c.</hi> 25. Hiſtor. Eccleſiaſt.</note> 
               <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> a blaſphemous Heretick, even in the dayes of the Apoſtles themſelves, who daringly avouching the Lord Chriſt to be no more than a meer man, and borne after the common way of humane generation (which gave occaſion to S. <hi>John,</hi> that ſoaring<note n="a" place="margin">Euch. 1.10.</note> Eagle, to write that his ſo ſublime Goſpel, wherein, in the very<note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 1.1, 2, &amp;c.</note> entrance of it (He proves his Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) He gave out, that after the reſurrection, there ſhould be in the great City <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> an outward way of pomp, and a kinde of voluptuous indulgence to corporall vanityes, and delights, during the terme of a thouſand yeares; which opinion He was thought to have ſucked from the Breaſts of the Jewiſh Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, that people miſtaking the nature and quality of Chriſts<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 20.21. A &amp;. 1.6.</note> Kingdome, thinking it to be after an externall glory, and not (as it is indeed) conſiſting<note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 17 21.</note> within, in the ſoule, after a<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 14.17.</note> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rirtuall manner, ruling and raigning over the ſpirituall part of man: But this Blaſphemer being exploded, and cryed down by all the Primitively-Orthodox Fathers, and Chriſtians, as the Hiſtoryes of thoſe Times informe us.</p>
            <p>The next, who moſt clearely ſpeak of it, or was, indeed, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the firſt who more directly vented the opinion, was one
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:125020:13"/>
               <hi>Papias</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hieropolis,</hi> as<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb.</hi> l. 3. c. 36. Eccl. Hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> acquaints us, a man of a weak and ſlender judgement, who if not utterly neglecting, yet but ſlightly valuing the Authority of the Holy Scriptures, pretended for his conceit, Apoſtolicall Traditions; and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the venerable name of Antiquity, it is not to be denyed, but that ſome of the ancient Fathers received ſome tang of the ſame opinion from him, as may be ſeen, or collected of<note n="g" place="margin">Juſtin: Martyr, <hi>Dialog.</hi> Cum Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon Jud: <hi>pag. 239</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and in the end of <hi>Trajans</hi> time<note n="h" place="margin">Baron: <hi>in Annal. Ann: 118. ſect 2.</hi> &amp; Hieron. in Catalog. illuſtr. cap. de Papiâ.</note> 
               <hi>Apollinarius,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertul.</hi> l. 3. adverſ. <hi>Marc.</hi> c. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> (too much miſled by <hi>Montane</hi> and <hi>Lactantius</hi>) who were in part ſpiced with this Millenariſme; ſo perilous a thing, it proves to the Supine, and out of a ſecure or careleſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard, to ſuffer Humane Tradition to become a Diotrephes, and to have the<note n="l" place="margin">3 Epiſt. John 9.</note> preheminence above the infallibity of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Scriptures; which ſacred, and unerring written Word of God doth hold forth (as of certaine credibility inſpired by the Divine, and firſt verity that can never deceive) no ſuch clear truth, that the Lord Chriſt ſhall in Perſon before the General Reſurrection, come viſibly, and corporally upon the earth, and as by a<note n="m" place="margin">Re 20.6.</note> firſt reſurrection cauſe all thoſe who dyed<note n="n" place="margin">Re. 14.13.</note> in, and for him, to ariſe, and with him in a peacefull tranquility, and glory to reigne, and to beare ſway over the wicked, as Vaſſals, for a thouſand yeares; which date of time being expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, immediately ſhall enſue the General Reſurrection, and the day of the laſt Judgement. No ſuch evidentiall verity is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated in Holy Writ, as of Abſolute Neceſſity to be believed unto ſalvation: But whatſoever is alledged out of the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Scriptures for the ſtabliſhing of that opinion, is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, either of the firſt coming of Chriſt in the fleſh, or of the ſtate of the N. T. in generall; or elſe, of the glorious eſtate of the Church triumphant to be expected hereafter in the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Kingdome for ever in Heaven, as<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh: Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard,</hi> loc. com. <hi>To.</hi> 9. c 7. ſect. 80</note> 
               <hi>Gerard</hi> judiciouſly: I have not time to alledge, or you patience to heare, on this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, the ſeverall Texts cited by the Chiliaſts, or of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox; many<note n="p" place="margin">See Biſh. <hi>Hall</hi> in his <hi>Revelations unrevealed,</hi> edit. 1650. D. <hi>Prid:</hi> ſerm. on 2 Pet. 3.13. &amp; ſerm. on Joh. 6.14. <hi>Per.</hi> Dem. of <hi>Probl.</hi> vid. Dierer. <hi>In die feſt. Bar.</hi> Ap. p. 7 14. &amp;c. vol. 4. <hi>Bul.</hi> l. 2. c. 11. con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. Anabapt. &amp; ſixt. Senenſ. l. 6. Annot. 347.</note> reverend, and renowned Divines have eaſed us all of that labour; let it ſuffice, at the preſent, to take notice, from our Saviours own lips, that <hi>his Kingdome is not of this world, John</hi> 18.36. but <hi>within us, Luke</hi> 17.21. and <hi>from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> and beſides, we finde, in our Creed (which is founded on<note place="margin">
                  <hi>k Lactant.</hi> l. 7 c. 24. <hi>Inſtitut.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:125020:13"/>the Scriptures, and may in every article thereof be<note n="q" place="margin">Art. 6. of the Ch: of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> proved by them) we finde, I ſay, in our Creed, mention made but of two viſible comings of Chriſt, the firſt in<note n="r" place="margin">Phil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8. Mat. 21.5.</note> Humility to ſuffer, and to be judged; the other, at the end of the world (but not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) in the<note n="s" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.17.</note> glory of his Father, to<note n="t" place="margin">Acts 17.31. 2 Tim. 4.1. 1 Pet. 4.5.</note> judge the world, both quick and dead in righteouſneſſe; and unto them that look for him, ſaith the great Apoſtle, ſhall he appear, the [<note n="u" place="margin">See my Sermon, ſtiled <hi>The Grand Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes,</hi> pag. 37. edit. 1653. preached at <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi>
               </note> ſecond] time, without ſinne, that is, without ſuffering any more as a ſacrifice for ſin unto ſalvation, <hi>Heb</hi> 8.28.</p>
            <p>Leaving then thoſe Millenarian conjectures to ſuch as abound with leiſure; reſt we in the ſolid determination of Orthodox, and ſtable judgements, who reſolve by the day, and by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing here mentioned in this text, to be meant the laſt great day of the generall Judgment, according to that Scripture <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. and the Lord Chriſt his ſecond<note n="w" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.1.</note> coming upon that day, in<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 25.31.</note> glorious Majeſty, unto the judgement of all the wolrd: ſo that however, thoſe who<note n="x" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.17.</note> labour in the Word and Doctrine, meet often with ſo great diſcouragements, that they ſeem to <hi>labour all in vaine, and ſpend their ſtrength for nought,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.4. yet <hi>ſurely their Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is with the Lord, and their worke,</hi> that is, the reward of their work is <hi>with the Lord;</hi> his goodneſſe is laid up for them; O how great! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.19. In the mean time, let it be our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and contentment that we<note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 24.46.</note> doe our Maſters work, not as by <hi>conſtraint,</hi> but<note n="z" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>willingly;</hi> ſith indeed ſuch a vertuous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ever carryeth its owne reward with it, as being a thing to be deſired, and embraced for its own worth; and certainly that ſweet comfort, and complacency that a righteous ſoule findeth in the ſincere diſcharge of his duty (within its proper ſtation) in conſcience of God, is infinitely more valuable than all the<note n="a" place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 11.25.</note> treaſures the earth can afford without it; only, as the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, we may not anticipate the ſeaſon of the Harveſt, but we muſt<note n="b" place="margin">Jam. 5.7</note> wait, &amp; then in due time, we ſhall reap, if we faint not, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.36.37. &amp; when the reward actually cometh, it (being ſo large) will abundantly recompence all our work, yea, end all our patience too; ſith the manner of it will be the more manifeſt, and conſpicuous before all in that great day, when<note n="c" place="margin">Rev. 20.12.</note> all, of all ſorts, both great and ſmall, ſhall, upon the generall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:125020:14"/>ſummons, ſtand before the laſt Tribunall, and then upon <hi>the appearance of the Chiefe Shepheard, we ſhall receive a Crown of Glory that fadeth not away,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.4.</p>
            <p>Hereof S. <hi>Paul</hi> had a particular aſſurance in his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, when he ſaith, <hi>Henceforth is laid up for [me] a Crowne of Righteouſneſſe;</hi> and if for him, why may it not be alſo poſſible for others to be in like manner aſſured of the ſame, eſpecially provided, that we are ſuch as do love his appearing?</p>
            <p>This queſtion, I confeſſe, is ſolid, yet ſuch, as wanteth not its intricacies: The Roman Catholicks in this controverſie are wont to reſolve thus, that indeed for ſo great a Saint, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> was, this aſſurance might be poſſible, yea, was attained to by Revelation extraordinary, by meanes of his <hi>fides privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giata,</hi> his ſpecial and priviledged faith, which as an Apoſtle, and a<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 9.15.</note> choſen veſſel of honour, he was endowed and adorned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all from Heaven; for that God had a great<note n="e" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.17.</note> ſervice for him to do, who was ſelected, as it were, to take up the Gauntlet in the quarrel of the Goſpel, againſt the manifold, fierce, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 16.9.</note> Adverſaries of the ſame, ſo that (as I ſaid in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) to ſteele his reſolution with the greater courage, he was fortifyed before-hand, and armed with an extraordinary aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a glorious reward, after his work, and warfaring there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was over:<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quer. </seg>
               </label> But now, whether this aſſurance be poſſible for an ordinary Chriſtian, by the uſe of ordinary lawfull means to attaine, is the next diſquiſition? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> To which the reſolution is affirmative, the thing is poſſible, though confeſſedly very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult: and this poſſibility is both <hi>Certitudine Objecti,</hi> and alſo <hi>Certitudine Subjecti;</hi> both, as it is ſure in it ſelf, as it is determin'd by God; &amp; likewiſe, in the particular evidence, &amp; ſpeciall expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the ſame in the ſoule of a true believer: and this is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, partly from thoſe Scriptures, which exhort unto a diligent endeavour after it, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. Now, the nature of Evangelicall precepts, and exhortations, in a contradiſtinction to thoſe of the Law, is, that they carry a ſpirit, a ſecret energy, vertue, and power with them, inabling, through grace, unto obſervation, therefore the Goſpel is called<note n="g" place="margin">John 6.63.</note> 
               <hi>life</hi> and <hi>spirit,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. and <hi>I can do all things through Chriſt that strengthens me,</hi> Phil. 4.13. partly alſo, this is proved from one principall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:125020:14"/>end of the ſpirits Donation, his being given us, namely, <hi>That we may know the things that are freely given unto us of God, and to co-witneſſe with our ſpirits, that we are his Sons and Daughters,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.12. Rom. 8.16. 1 John 5.13. Thirdly, from the duties required of us, upon this account, as, <hi>thankfulneſſe, Epheſ.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12, 13. What wiſe man will give thanks for that, which he hath no certainty that he doth enjoy? this were for a man to boaſt of a<note n="h" place="margin">Prov 25 14.</note> falſe gift, as of a<note n="i" place="margin">Jud. v.12</note> cloud without water: ſo likewiſe of Love, <hi>we love God, becauſe he first loved us,</hi> 1 John 4.19. in ſo freely giving his <hi>Son</hi> to us. <hi>John</hi> 3.16. and together with him <hi>all things</hi> that do accompany ſalvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. even to be <hi>the Author of life and ſalvation unto all that obey him,</hi> Heb. 5.9. And how come we to know of all this love, but by that experimentall proofe thereof, that is <hi>ſhed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghoſt, which is given unto us?</hi> Rom. 5.5. And laſtly, by the examples of Saints that have had this aſſurance in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as <hi>Job</hi> 19.25. <hi>Abraham, Rom.</hi> 4.21. and here, in my Text, Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> which eminent Saints were not ſet forth in Holy Writ, as Wonders, meerely to be gazed at, but as Patternes of imitation; and though ordinary Chriſtians and Saints cannot reach to the ſame ſteps, yet they may walk in the ſame path, and may poſſibly attaine, though not to the ſame meaſures, yet to the ſame foundneſſe of perſwaſion; and indeed, as a reverend<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>B. King,</hi> lect. 38. on <hi>Joan.</hi>
               </note> Divine obſerves its firmneſſe, rather than fulneſſe of aſſurance, (namely, in reſpect of adherence, or of recumbency) that the Saints in this life arrive unto, but to this firmneſſe they may come by the uſe of the ordinary, and of the right means, as here S. <hi>Paul</hi> did by <hi>fighting the good fight,</hi> by <hi>finiſhing his courſe,</hi> and by <hi>keeping the faith;</hi> hereby, as by the ordinary meanes, he concluded (therein likewiſe ſhewing us an example) that from <hi>henceforth there was a Crowne of Righteouſneſſe laid up in Heaven for him,</hi> yea, and for all others with himſelfe, who loved the appearing of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>But, though it be (cautionately underſtood) thus poſſible; notwithſtanding it is very difficult, and hard to be attained, and that for many weighty, and important reaſons. As</p>
            <p>Firſt, in regard of the difficulty to put a diſtinction between ſeeming Vertues, and reall Graces, which are the ſignes, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:125020:15"/>fruits of Election, and which give the beſt evidence of glory; ſo that there needs much diſcuſſion, and an exact ſpirit of<note n="l" place="margin">Phil. 1.9, 10.</note> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, to put a Difference, and to diſcriminate the one from the other; yea, we are to take notice, that there are many Vices neere of<note n="*" place="margin">Fallie cnim viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate, honi.</note> kinne to many Vertues, and carry in ſemblance, a neare affinity, as it were, with them; There is, ſaith devout <hi>Bernard, à minium virtutis,</hi> a certaine kinde of Vermilion, wherewith Satan paints over the outſide of Vices, and makes them ſhew like Vertues, and but by an Eye and an Heart<note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 5: 14.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in piety hardly diſcernable each from the other; thus Flattery ſometimes carryes the ſtyle of affability; Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Frugality; Raſhneſſe of Fortitude; a Divelliſh Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiaveliſme, of a lawfull policy; exceſſe and ryot, of good fellowſhip; and under this miſtake of judgement, that is taken for zeale, which is nothing but an impetuous<note n="n" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.4.</note> headineſſe, or a fiery kinde of vehemency, that in ſtead of heating the houſe, is apt to burne it; Thus in ſhort, preſumption paſſeth often for Faith, this being the<note n="o" place="margin">Jer. 17.9. 2 Cor. 11 3.</note> guile of our hearts, and Satan complying with it, (who can transforme himſelfe into an<note n="p" place="margin">2 Cor. 11 14.</note> Angell of Light) and ſet a faire gloſſe upon naughty wares, making the tinſell of Hypocriſie to paſſe for the Silver of ſincerity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we muſt not too much relye upon our<note n="q" place="margin">Prov. 3.5.</note> owne Judgements in this matter, but bring things to the<note n="r" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.21.</note> beame of the Sanctuary, and there<note n="s" place="margin">Rom. 12.2.</note> prove and weigh them; the Word of God ever giveth right Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the ſearching hereinto, <hi>John</hi> 5.39.<note n="t" place="margin">Act 17.11.</note> and examining of theſe matters, hereby requiring great deliberation, this makes the aſſurance difficult, when the Evidence is perplexed, and not preſently cleared.</p>
            <p>Secondly, its hard, in regard of the plenty of Luſts, and of the<note n="u" place="margin">Gal. 5.19.</note> workes of the fleſh, which too much over-grow, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in every mans Heart; but graces are but rare, and come up thin, much chaffe and little ſolid graine; our graces are like <hi>Gideons</hi> Army, but a handfull in compariſon, but our ſinnes and like <hi>Midiknites,</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Jude 7.12.</note> Innumerable as Graſhoppers; Hipps and Hawes (ſaith one) grow in every hedge, when choycer fruits are but in ſome few Gardens; and every ſoyle almoſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yeilds ſtone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and rubbiſh, but Gold and precious ſtones are found in very few places; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nw S. <hi>Peter,</hi> who exhorts to give diligence
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:125020:15"/>to make Election ſure, exhorts alſo, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6. to adde to Faith, Vertue, to Vertue, Knowledge, &amp;c. a large enumerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or induction of graces is required to clear up this aſſurance, and certainly that is a matter of no eaſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, (that I may haſten) this is difficult, in regard of the great progreſſe, that an Hypocrite, or a Caſt-away, may make in the wayes of Chriſtianity, and yet never attaine to this aſſurance; He may have ſome degrees of Illumination, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4. much like a Coruſcation, that a ſuddaine flaſh of Lightning maketh in the Ayre; He may have good wiſhes as <hi>Balaam, Numbers</hi> 23.10. A ſight of ſinne as <hi>Cain</hi> had, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.13. Confeſſe ſinne as <hi>Judas</hi> did, <hi>Matthew</hi> 27.4. have zeale as <hi>Jehu</hi> had, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.16. in theſe, and in like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gifts may a very Caſt-away make a great progreſſe; But no child of God can have any reall comfort in any thing, wherein he cannot ſay, he hath (yet) therein gone beyond a Caſt-away; and yet, but in the ground, or rule, or end of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, theſe things are hardly diſcernable each from other: All which, and much more that might be added to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſhew, though not the utter impoſſibility, yet ſurely the very great difficulty of attaining unto this aſſurance, that a man can ſay, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth here, in a particular application unto his ſoule, Chriſt loved [me] and gave himſelfe for [me,] and <hi>henceforth is laid up for</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>[me] a Crown of Righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There yet remaines but one Pearle more in the Cabinet of this Text, which I ſhall onely offer to your ſhort notice, and ſo conclude, it is that due qualification which renders other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as well as it did S. <hi>Paul,</hi> capable of the <hi>Crown of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> they muſt be ſuch, as who do love the Lord Chriſt's <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond appearing</hi> in the day of Judgement. And, indeed, it is the property of none but Saints, to <hi>love it,</hi> and <hi>long for it.</hi> See <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. Rev. 22.20. <hi>Amen</hi> even ſo come Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Some cautions, notwithſtanding, muſt be here remembred, ſith it's poſſible that times may fall out, when we tremble at the thought, or mention of it; as when conſcience is wounded afreſh with ſome groſs act of ſin: this made <hi>David</hi> afraid, yea, to roar out, and to make a noyſe through the diſquietneſſe of his ſpirit, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.2. and, under that ſtate of ſoul,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:125020:16"/>to begg earneſtly to be ſpared, that he might recover ſtrength (in Gods favour) before he went hence, and was no more, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.13. or elſe, when the Lord ſhall, for divers ends and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſurcharge the ſoule and conſcience with the ſins of youth, for which, perhaps, men have not, as became them, been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently humbled; thus, dealt he even with his ſervant <hi>Job,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting bitter things againſt him, <hi>Job</hi> 13.26. ſee alſo <hi>Job</hi> 1.6.4.</p>
            <p>But, out of thoſe caſes, it is <hi>proprium quarto modo,</hi> onely the Saints love it, all ſuch love it, and alwayes: and no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, ſith by this ſecond coming, and appearance of Chriſt in the day of the laſt Judgement, they receive very great and ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable benefits, ſuch as are finall Redemption of the Body from corruption, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. Freedome from the ſociety of the wicked, which here<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 119.136.</note> afflict the godly by their violation of Gods Law and Precepts; Deliverance, not onely from the<note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 6.12.</note> raigne, and<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 19.13.</note> dominion, but even from the inhabitation and being of ſin, which here they finde as a clogg, and a<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 38.4.</note> burthen to<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 11.28.</note> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy for them, and ſo long to be rid of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. and laſtly, the beatifical<note n="d" place="margin">1 Joh. 3.2.</note> viſion, and perfect fruition of the ever-bleſſed, and all-glorious Trinity, in the<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 12 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>, 23, 24.</note> Heavenly Hieruſalem, among the innumerable company of Angels, being admitted to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly, and Church of the firſt-borne, which are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled and written in Heaven, and to God the Judge of all and to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, and to Jeſus the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the New Covenant; in whoſe <hi>preſence</hi> there is <hi>fulneſſe of joy,</hi> and at whoſe <hi>right hand are pleaſures for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, my brethren, after my meaſure, as I could (upon ſo ſhort notice of about a day) though not ſo fully after my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, as I would, in ſo great, ſo learned, and ſerious an Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, have I diſpatched my diſcourſe upon this Scripture; your candour will, I hope, connive at the want of poliſhing, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine it as it is, according to the weight, and importance of the matter of it: And may the<note n="g" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.10.</note> God of all grace reap the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall<note n="h" place="margin">1 Tim 1.17.</note> glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:125020:16"/>
            <head>An ENCOMIUM of M. <hi>Abraham Wheelock,</hi> B.D.</head>
            <head type="sub">Late Proſeſſor of <hi>Arabick</hi> and <hi>Saxon</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S concerning our reverend, and learned Brother deceaſed. Mr. <hi>Abraham Wheelock,</hi> Batchelar in Divinity, many yeares fellow of <hi>Clare Hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridge;</hi> I could ſeriouſly have wiſhed that ſome ſilver Trampet of that Univerſity (to which he was an ornament, within his ſtation) had ſounded out his Encomium upon this occaſion: He was there beſt knowne, where Learning, of all ſorts, is now in the Zenith, and the exquiſite perfection in the Tongues (much advanced by his skill) in the very Tropick of <hi>Cancer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, ſith it is now fallen to my lot, I may more truly ſay of him, than<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Paterc.</hi> l. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Paterculus</hi> did of <hi>AE milius Paulus, Vir in tantum laudandus fuit, in quantum Virtus ipſa intelligi poteſt,</hi> He was a man to be praiſed, ſo farre as vertue it ſelfe can be underſtood, he therein, indeed, being as the Moon at the<note n="b" place="margin">Eccleſ. 50.6.</note> full.</p>
            <p>For his Theologicall part, a Divine of<note n="c" place="margin">Tit. 1.9.</note> Orthodex judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of a<note n="d" place="margin">Tim. 2.2.</note> godly, an<note n="e" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.12.</note> exmeplary, and of a<note n="f" place="margin">Prov. 11.30. Dan. 12.3. 1 Pec. 3.1.</note> winning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,<note n="g" place="margin">1 Tim 3.3. Heb. 13.5.</note> abhorring covetouſneſſe, who did both <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, rightly<note n="h" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.15.</note> divide that word of truth after which he walked with<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> ſtrait ſteps to his feet: wee might have read in his<note n="*" place="margin">Noclur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni juvat
[impallc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſare] char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is.</note> pale countenance the expreſſe Characters of his unwearied induſtry, and ſtudies; <hi>cujus vultum nec fuſcavit maeror, nec levigavit riſus,</hi> as s.<note n="k" place="margin">S Bern. de Mac.</note> 
               <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> wrote of his friend <hi>Malachy;</hi> be carried mortificati
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:125020:17"/>on in his very looks; continuing, without interruption, a constant and<note n="l" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Rom. 12.15. Pſ. 1226. H.b. 12.14.</note> peacefull ſon of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> herein exerciſing Himſelfe to have alwayes a † Conſcience void of offence toward God, and toward men: Thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, mentioned by the learned Apoſtle,<note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.28.</note> diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or kinds of Tongues, he was in much variety, from Heaven ſuperlatively endowed with, by the gift of Gods ſpirit: He being ſo eminent a Linguiſt, he might have ſaid (without envy, or diſparagement to any be it ſpoken) I thank my God I ſpeak with<note n="n" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.18.</note> Tongues more than moſt of them all; the intricacies whereof he had a faculty, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all a facility hoth to finde out, and to make pervious, eluci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dating what was obſcure, enucleating what hard, that as the <hi>Jewiſh Rabbins,</hi> ſo oft as they met with Texts, which were as <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſaith, of ſome things in <hi>S. Paul's</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="o" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16.</note> hard to be underſtood, out of which they could not extricate themſelves, were went to ſhut up all their diſcourſe with this, <hi>Elias cum venerit, ſolver dubia, Elias</hi> ſhall anſer this doubt, when he comes; in like ſort was he as another <hi>Elias</hi> to the doubts and difficulties of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who (being<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>D. Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fot</hi> Mr. of <hi>Katharine</hi> Hall in <hi>Camridge</hi> in his <hi>Harmory.</hi>
               </note> accurate in the Rabbinicall Learning were very well able to judge: gave him this teſtimony a good while ſince in print, that ſcarcely anything, that way, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved too hard for him, for his condation or deciſian.</p>
            <p>Yet one thing I cannot but obſerve to you of him whom I ſo well, and ſo long knew) and it is this, That whereas his experience found that ſentence of <hi>Thucydides</hi> a most au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick verity, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the leſſe the Art, uſually the more the vaunting, but the more Ratiocination, the ſlower the Determination; ſuitably to that of the great Dactor of the Gentiles, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball anced know ledge, like a bladder blowne up with wind,<note n="q" place="margin">1 Cor. 8.1.</note> puffeth and ſwelleth with oſtentation; waking many (out
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:125020:17"/>of en overweening upon their ſuperficiall excellencies) as <hi>Antipheron Orietes</hi> (in <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) to imagine, that every where they ſee their own ſhapes and pictures going before them; yet, that I ſay, which I obſerved remarkable, and wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of univerſall imitation in him, was, under his many and exceeding abilities, his humble and exeeding modeſtie; ſo that others took more notice of him, than he did of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; much like to the Violet, a flower of a ſweet and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous ſcent, yet groweth loweſt in the Garden, covering it ſelfe often with its owne leaves: Howbeit, as the odorife rous fragrancy thereof cannot but be diſcovered; ſo he, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his accompliſhments, could not be concealed; yea, as<note n="r" place="margin">Eccleſ. 50.6.</note> 
               <hi>Syracides</hi> ſaid of <hi>Simon</hi> the Son of <hi>Onias,</hi> he was as the morning Star in the midſt of a Clound. His ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and, withall, his integrity having made him thus known; to his cuſtody, and ever ſight were committed the rich Treaſives of Learning, laid up in the choice Library of the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge:</hi> And about two and twenty yeares paſt, beyend his owne expectation, though not beyend his merit, he was choſen the firſt publique profeſſor, and reader of <hi>Arabick</hi> there; A Lecture firſt founded at the ſote and proper charges of an eminent and truly religious Gentleman of this Citie of <hi>London</hi> (to which having, like him ſelfe, bornall the principall offices therein, he hath long been an honour) Mr. Alderm. <hi>Thomas Adams,</hi> who ever ſince continned is by his bounty to him, of full <hi>40 l. per annum,</hi> conſtantly paid; for which munificent Act he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves of all Schollars (whom <hi>co nomine,</hi> he affectionately regardeth) an honour able mention, and of all learned po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity and<note n="s" place="margin">pſ. 112.6.</note> everlaſting memoriall. <hi>Et memorem famam qui bene geſſit, habet.</hi> Ovid. To this worthy Citizen, of ſo high a<note n="t" place="margin">Gal. 2.2.</note> reputation; muſt be added the example of a noble Knight, to whom, and to whoſe Heires (inheriting his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:125020:18"/>and<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. iſocrat. <hi>Vid</hi> 1 Reg. 5.7.</note> vertues, as well as his lands) the Common wealth of Literature reſts deeply engaged, by name Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> (of pious memory) who, with great expence of time and treaſure, restored many precious monuments of antiquity (very uſefull to Gods Church and very tart<note n="*" place="margin">Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum quaſi moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum.</note> war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings to pitchy Sacriledge) from duſt and obſcurity, to beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and light: who, at his owne coſt, firſt erected, about ten yeares paſt, a <hi>Saxon</hi> Lecture in the ſame Univerſity, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing it by an Annuall Penſion of <hi>20 l.</hi> which was ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by his learned<note n="†" place="margin">Sr. John Spelman.</note> Son; and ſince, continued by his<note n="*" place="margin">M. Roger Spelman.</note> Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child (a Gentleman of gallant ingenuity) ſo that what the Poet ſaid of the golden branch holds true in that Progeny,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note n="w" place="margin">Virgil. An.</note> 
                  <hi>Uno avulſo non deficit alter</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aureus, &amp; ſimili frondeſcit virga metallo.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>when one failes, another of the ſame metall buddeth forth, and flouriſheth: And this Lecture alſo was firſt publickly read by this ſame Profeſſor: Both which he diſcharged with ſo compleat abilities, as found acceptation of all, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration in many, hopes of imitation but in a few. yet this was not all, but as when the clowds are full, they drop down, the eares ſhed, and the fountaines flow out; even ſo his goodneſſe became ſtill diffuſive, and was very communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to others, even to the moſt diſtant and remote Nations; for which purpoſe he ſpent himſelfe, as a candle in the ſoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, to the very laſt blaze, whilſt he was here publiſhing the foure Goſpels of our Saviour, with acute and ſolid Annoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in the Perſian Tongue; in the progreſſe of which work, it pleaſed God to call him<note n="x" place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.5.</note> home to his happineſſe with himſelf in Heaven: but as S.<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>S</hi> Ambr. De obitu <hi>Vaientin.</hi> Imper. S. <hi>Aug.</hi> de Bapt <hi>l 4. c. 22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writes of the deſire, and vowed reſolution of Baptiſme in <hi>Valentinian,</hi> that being diſappointed, by providence, of the Act thereof, in reſpect of the outward ſigne, yet God giving him the grace of that Sacrament, he was accepted as a Chriſtian;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:125020:18"/>and as S. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s attempt in offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his onely Son, upon a Divine command, ſtyleth it an<note n="z" place="margin">Jam 2.21.</note> actuall offering of him, for that in the ſerious prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his minde, he really, and fiduciarily intended it, though the ſtory acquaints us, that the thing it ſelfe was<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 22. 11, 12.</note> prevented by an heavenly Angel: ſo the indefatigable endeavours of this pious undertaker are interpreted, as a full diſpatch of that work, by his gracious God,</p>
            <p>And that which yet farther adds a luſtre to his praiſes, is, the ample Teſtimony given of him both Living, and Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by that oracle of all imaginable learning that full ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazine of all ſanctified Devotion, the glory of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the wonder of Chriſtendome, and the triumgh of the holy Angels, who guard and protect him for good. Dr. <hi>Uſner,</hi> the L. <hi>Primate</hi> of <hi>Armagh:</hi> as likewiſe by that famous Antiquary, and living library, Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> of whoſe tranſcendencies in the Orientall Tongues, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundities, beſides his Claſsicall Preheminence in all manner of History, and skill in the Lawes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I might write even a voluminous Encomiastick, but that (through a ſecret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciouſneſſe of my own tenuity) I feare, that I ſhould but dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo ſhining a Topaze by my rude poliſhing: <hi>Certes,</hi> its a verity, what from that Patriark of Philoſophers (as that incomparable Writer of the Eccleſiaſticall policy, Mr. <hi>Hoo ker,</hi> styles<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſtot.</hi> in Ethic.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) is received, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> honour reflects with beams of brightneſſe,<note place="margin">Non poteſt benus uon eſſe, qui be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis placet. S. <hi>Bern, ep. 248.</hi>
               </note> and ſplendor upon the perſons honouring is mord conſpicuous; ſuch as of theſe now mentioned is, who, in their ſeverall excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, have lighted up Tapers to the Chriſtian world, for its illumination.</p>
            <p>Such was the eſteem of our Brother, whom, ſith the world was not<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 11. 38.</note> worthy of him, we finde as another <hi>Enoch</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Gen 5.24.</note> wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:125020:19"/>with God, to be tranſlated to his bliſſe; Heaven having gained a Saint triumphant, whilſt we, for the preſent, miſſe him in the Church militant.</p>
            <p>Miſse him did I ſay? Yea, at this inſtant ſeaſon, his loſſe is moſt conſiderable, there being ſo much need of his ſhoulder under that Herculean labour, and burthen, that now lyeth upon many worthy renowned Doctors, and eximious Divines, of this our Church of <hi>England,</hi> who are now about ☞ to publiſh the Holy Bible in a greater variety of Tongues, and Tranſlations, than ever have been, hitherto, ſeen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant [together;] their Lamps, I truſt, ſhall never want oyl, till that maugre the impoſtures of undermining <hi>Jeſuitiſme,</hi> of phrentick <hi>Anabaptiſme,</hi> or of Atheiſticall <hi>Barbariſme</hi>) both the Light, and the Heat of the<note n="e" place="margin">Mal. 4.2.</note> Sun of Righteouſneſſe Chriſt Jeſus, hath enlightned the eyes, and warmed the breasts of ſuch as belong to Gods election, even unto the<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 19.4, 5, 6.</note> ends of the earth.</p>
            <p>I have onely thus much to adde farther, which alſo accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulates his commendations, that it may be well ſaid of him, what is recorded of righteous <hi>Abel, Being dead, yet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or, is yet ſpoken of<note n="g" place="margin">Heb 11.4.</note> Nor can his memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry die, whilſt ſo many hopefull plants of his ſetting, ſpring up after him, and daily grow famous in <hi>Cambridge:</hi> And which I much rejoyce that I have occaſion to mention, (my ſelfe having beene ſometimes a Member of that Society) the <hi>Palme</hi> for skill in the <hi>Orientall Languages</hi> may well be given to <hi>Kings Colledge;</hi> unto ſome preſent<note n="*" place="margin">M. <hi>Rich. Hunt.</hi> Mr. <hi>H: Auſtin,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Fellowes</hi> whereof (having atteined a large meaſure of perfection that way) the inſpection and correction of the preſse, to perfect the printing of the <hi>Perſian Goſpells,</hi> was wiſhed, and much intruſted, by the deceaſed <hi>Profeſſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what ſhall I<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 11.32.</note> more ſay? The time would faile me to mention the Catalogue of perſons of<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 16.7.</note> Note, who as the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>k</hi> Phil. 2.29.1.</note>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:125020:19"/>
               <hi>Philippians</hi> did <hi>Epaphroditus,</hi> honoured him living; and ſince his deceaſe have teſtified their regards by becoming Benefactors to thoſe of his nearest relations, as the learned Mr. <hi>Joh. Sadler,</hi> Maſter of <hi>Mag:</hi> Coll: in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> M. <hi>Caſſels,</hi> and divers others of eſteem among Schollars. But, <hi>quorſum haec?</hi> to what purpoſe is all this profuſe Panegy. rick? may ſome<note n="l" place="margin">Act. 18.17.</note> 
               <hi>Gallio</hi> ſay, one, I mean, who careth for none of thoſe things; ſith without humane Tongues, Arts, or Sciences, yea, without Schools, or Academyes, men may be all taught of God, and Heaven it ſelf undoubtedly obtained? To ſuch <hi>Julians,</hi> who would tumble down all Schooles of Learning, leſt their Enthuſiaſticall irrationalities might be (as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> gives the reaſon of that Apoſtate) pierced thorow by ſharp arrows<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Nazian.</note> feathered from thence; to ſuch I ſay, I would have the ſin laid to their Hearts, though my charity prompts me to pray, as S. <hi>Stephen,</hi> that it may<note n="n" place="margin">Act. 7 60.</note> not be laid to their charge.</p>
            <p>We find mention made of the<note n="o" place="margin">2 Kings 6.1.</note> place of the ancient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and of their Sons, and<note n="*" place="margin">2 Kings 9.1.</note> Children educated (no doubt)<note n="*" place="margin">See 1 Cor 14.32.</note> [under] them, and inſtructed in their way: we read even of our Saviour himſelf (in his youth) that he delighted to ſit in the<note n="p" place="margin">Luk. 2.46.</note> midſt of the D<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. both hearing them, &amp; asking them queſtions; though in him were<note n="q" place="margin">Col. 2.3.</note> hid all the treaſures of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge: And S. <hi>Paul</hi> was frequent in School-diſputations, <hi>Act. 19.9.</hi> And whereas ſome have ſaid, that many great Philoſophers have bin very unſound in belief; It may be poſsible, when that skil is unſanctifyed; but otherwiſe, (without all controverſie) many very ſound in the Chriſtian belief, have bin alſo great Philoſophers: <hi>Moſes</hi> was<note n="r" place="margin">Acts 8.22.</note> learned in all the wiſdome of <hi>Egypt;</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Dan 4.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel,</hi> of <hi>Chaldee; Job</hi> not unexpert in<note n="t" place="margin">Job 38.31, 32.</note> Aſtronomy;<note n="u" place="margin">Jer. 32.44. Am. 6.5. 2 Sam. 23.1.</note> 
               <hi>Jer.</hi> in the common Laws of his time, <hi>David</hi> in <hi>w</hi> Muſique,<note n="x" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.18.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> in the Tongues, in<note n="y" place="margin">Act. 17.28. Tit. 1.12.</note> Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and in all the knowledge both of <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:125020:20"/>and the Hiſtoryes of the Church acquaint us of <hi>Cyprian, Optatus, Lactantius,</hi> S. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> (a Father mightily ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> and <hi>Lucian</hi>'s Dialogues) and many others laden out of <hi>Egypt</hi> with the treaſures, and ſpoiles of that Learning, being better inſtructed for Gods ſervice by thoſe helps; as the Temple it ſelfe of God was forwarded in the ſtructure and ſtate thereof by the timber of Cedar and Firre that<note n="z" place="margin">1 Kings 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>Hiram</hi> (though an exotick <hi>Sidonian</hi> Prince) brought into that very building.</p>
            <p>And, indeed, I am clearely of opinion, that the reaſon, why ſo few <hi>Jews</hi> are converted, is the too remiſs regard of their Tongue, and Rabbinicall traditions, out of which (as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, Arnobius, Lactantius,</hi> and others, did in their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling heretofore with <hi>Ethnicks</hi>) till the vanity of their owne grounds be declared, and convinced, there is not ſo apparent hopes to win them over to become Christian: and it may be by a good providence (even for their ſeaſonable coalition into the ſame ſheepfold, under one and the ſame<note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 10.16.</note> Shepheard, Chriſt Jeſus) that their language and antiquityes are now ſo much ſtudyed in our Univerſities, as ſcarcely, with more criticall accuratneſs, in any age.</p>
            <p>It's true indeed, we ſhall be all taught of God, but it is me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, and by the ordinary means; In vaine ſhall there be an attempt to instill principles of Chriſtianity into either <hi>Jewes,</hi> or other <hi>Pagan</hi> Infidels, till the Speech, or Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of both be underſtood, which without learning in the Tongues, cannot feaſibly be atchieved: Herein our Brother (whoſe Obſequies we now ſolemnize) did excell, and ſo both doe, and will others alſo, who had the happineſſe of his Manuduction.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:125020:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
